Finding Aid for Ozone House Records, 1970-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ozone House Records
1970-2001
Ozone House.
968 Bj 2; Bj Out.
Shelter in Ann Arbor, Michigan, for runaway young people. The Ozone House records have been divided into seven series: Meeting Minutes; Grants and Funding; Worker Training; Publicity and Outreach; Topical Files; Drug Helpline; and Visual Materials. The records document the administration and various counseling, training, fundraising and outreach activities of the Ozone House.
10.5 linear feet in 11 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Ozone House (donor no. 8423 ) beginning in November 1995. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open to research, except where indicated.
Ozone House was founded in 1969 by members of the Ann Arbor community who were concerned about the many homeless runaways drawn to the area by the town's radical reputation. At that time Ann Arbor was part of a "runaway triangle", along with Florida and Berkeley, California, which drew runaway would-be hippies from all over the country. Ozone was meant to be a haven for young people who were unable to cope with life on the street, and was staffed mainly by volunteers who provided crisis counseling as well as advice, food and moral support. The organization has evolved in response to changes in society, for example its clients include fewer runaways and more teenagers forced to leave home involuntarily, but it has maintained its focus on the needs of young people and their families.
One of the oldest runaway shelters in the country, Ozone was originally part of the Community Center Coordinating Council [C4], which in the late 1960s provided social services to young people who either did not qualify for help from established human services agencies, or else did not feel comfortable dealing with them. Ozone began as a "crash pad" at St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, and took its name from a Commander Cody and the Lost Planet Airmen song: "Lost in the Ozone Again".
Since 1970, Ozone changed locations several times and has gradually become more cooperative with mainstream social service agencies and the police. However, as an organization, for many years it maintained a distinctive attitude which reflected its anti-establishment beginnings. This was due in large measure to its collective decision-making structure and heavy reliance on volunteers. Small collectives had authority to make some decisions regarding specific areas of service, such as training or fundraising. Collectives also assessed needs and suggested solutions, which were then brought forward for discussion by the General Body, which was composed of all paid staff, volunteers and the Board of Directors. All major policy issues and decisions were discussed by the General Body until consensus was reached. While the process could be slow and circuitous at times, Ozoners believed that it gave them a greater personal stake in how Ozone House was run.
Changing times and reliance on outside agencies for funding made it difficult to maintain Ozone's unusual administrative structure. By the early 1990s, trained professionals were doing work which in the past had been done by volunteers; this created some tension between old and new Ozone workers. Ozone's services had become more structured as well. In the organization's early days, staff sometimes resorted to "moling" - illegally placing minors in private homes when parents would not consent to placing them in foster care. But as outside funding became more difficult to attract and maintain, Ozone had to become more mainstream, and risks like "moling" were no longer taken.
Ozone's services also became more extensive during the 1980s. In 1984, Ozone founded Miller House, where homeless teenagers could receive free room and board while they worked and learned independent living skills. Although maintaining funding for Miller House has been a struggle, and it was forced to close for most of 1994, it has been a successful and innovative program.
The collective system was officially abandoned in March 1995, in favor of a more typical hierarchical administrative structure. Key responsibilities are carried out by paid staff rather than volunteers, whose main activity is to provide support on the crisis phone lines. Ozone's main services did not change, however, as it continues to provide help to runaways, as well as counseling, information, referrals, temporary foster care, and support groups for teenagers and their families.
The Ozone House records have been divided into eight series: Meeting Minutes; Grants and Funding; Worker Training; Publicity and Outreach; Topical Files; Drug Helpline; Visual Materials, and Worker to Worker Notebooks. The records document the administration and various counseling, training, fundraising and outreach activities of Ozone House.
Subjects:
Collectivism--Michigan.; Community Center Coordinating Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Counselors--Michigan.; Drug abuse--Michigan.; Drug abuse counseling--Michigan.; Drug utilization--Michigan.; Drug Helpline (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Foster home care--Michigan.; Group homes for teenagers--Michigan.; Miller House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ozone House.; Runaway teenagers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Social work with youth--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Teenagers--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ozone House.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Meeting Minutes, 1972-1992
  Meeting Minutes (2.5 linear ft.; 1972-1992) contains minutes, meeting agendas and notes from the groups and collectives which ran Ozone House for its first 25 years. These records reflect the unusual administrative structure of Ozone House, along with the successes and pitfalls of running a social service agency by group consensus. Because important decisions were made by the group at large rather than one or two senior administrators, the arguments for and against those decisions are often clearly spelled out in the meeting minutes. The series provides a detailed history of how the organization grew and changed over a twenty year period.
  - Backup Collective, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1972-1989; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Budget, Fundraising and Donations Collective, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Client Council Minutes and Activities, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Counseling Collective, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - General Body Meetings
    - 1983, 1987-1992; 9 folders (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 9)
      Closed until Jan. 1, 2041 ]
  - General Meetings, 1977-1984; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - General Body Notes, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - General Meetings, 1985-1987; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Long Range Planning Collective, 1976-1991; 1995; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Outreach Collective, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
  - Restructuring Meetings, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Salary Parity Collective, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meetings, 1975-1985; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Staff Meetings, 1986-1992; 10 folders (Box 3)
- Grants and Funding, 1974-1994
  Grants and Funding (1.5 linear ft.; 1974-1994) contains grant applications and correspondence which document the increasing amounts of time and energy that Ozone workers put into fundraising, especially since the early 1980s. The core of Ozone's funding since the mid-1970s has been a "Runaway Youth Project" Grant from the federal government's Department of Health and Social Services; the applications for this grant (box 4) provide a good overview of how the money was allocated, as well as how Ozone House was run. Other grant applications indicate what Ozone workers considered to be some of clients' most pressing needs, for example Transitional Living or Substance Free Support programs.
  - Action Grants, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Adolescent Training Program Grant, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Carry-over Grants, 1976-1981 (Box 3)
  - Children's Trust Fund Proposal, 1987 (Box 3)
  - City of Ann Arbor Funding, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Community Foundation for Southeastern Michigan, 1985 (Box 3)
  - County Money: Human Services Group, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Department of Social Services Homeless Youth Grant Proposal, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Family Oriented Services Grant Application, 1978 (Box 3)
  - First Martin Corporation Donation Requests, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising Information, 1977-1987 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising Letters, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Galen's Medical Fund, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Heart to Heart for the Homeless, 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Independent Living Program
    - Budget Proposals, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
    - Grant Materials, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Michigan State Housing Development Authority
    - Grant, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Homeless Children's Fund, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Miller House Grant, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Office of Youth Development Continuation Proposal, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Power Foundation, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Project Connections Volunteer Grant Application, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Red Cross Grant, 1984-1986 (Box 4)
  - "Runaway Youth Project" Grant Applications, 1975-1990; 5 folders; 5 volumes (Box 4)
  - Substance Free Support Program
    - Contract, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Grant Proposal, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Transitional Living Program Grants, 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Volunteer Training Program Grant Application, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw County Grant Applications, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw Intergenerational Supported Housing Projects, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw United Way
    - Application for Admission, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Grant Application, circa 1992 (Box 4)
  - Youth Development Bureau Grant Proposal: Adolescent Abuse and Neglect Demonstration Project, 1980 (Box 4)
- Worker Training, 1972-1993
  Worker Training (0.5 linear ft.; 1972-1993) includes training manuals, notes, job descriptions and contracts for volunteers and paid staff. This series gives perhaps the best sense of the responsibilities and counseling issues which Ozone workers dealt with on a daily basis. It also shows how volunteer workers, most without any previous experience as therapists, were trained to work as crisis counselors.
  - Backup Manuals, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Backup Training, 1977-1990; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Empathy Training, 1982-1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Group Dynamics Workshop, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Guidelines for Counseling Gay Clients, circa 1980s (Box 5)
  - Job Descriptions, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Guidelines and Planning Memos, circa 1980s (Box 5)
  - New Worker Training Manual, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Ozone House Peoples Handbook, circa 1970s (Box 5)
  - Rape Information, 1972-1974 (Box 5)
  - Resource of the Week, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Staff Manual, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Staff Manual for Backup Coordinators, circa 1980s (Box 5)
  - Staff Policies and Information, 1986-1990 (Box 5)
  - Substance Abuse Presentations, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Suicide Prevention Training, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Trainers' Manuals, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Training, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Training Collective Notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Worker Contracts, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Workshop Evaluations, 1993 (Box 5)
- Publicity and Outreach, 1971-1995
  Publicity and Outreach (0.5 linear ft.; 1971-1995) contains clippings, newsletters, press releases, presentation notes and promotional materials. Articles by and about Ozone House include the "We're People Too" advice column which was written by staff and ran in the Ann Arbor News between 1974 and 1981.
  - Board of Directors Newsletters and Correspondence, 1973-1982 (Box 5)
  - Community High Classes, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - "Find Yourself" Class at Community High, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Potential Newsletter Articles, undated (Box 5)
  - Presentation and Outreach Notes, 1989-1993; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Presentation Notes, 1981-1990s (Box 5)
  - Press Releases and Public Service Announcements, 1976-1990 (Box 5)
  - Promotional Material, circa 1970s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Publicity, circa 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - "We're People Too" Newspaper Column, 1974-1981; 3 folders (Box 6)
- Drug Helpline, 1973-1976
  Drug Helpline (5 folders; 1973-1976) is another C4 organization which shared space with Ozone during the 1970s. These anonymous call records provide an unusual glimpse of recreational drug use in Ann Arbor during the early 1970s.
  - Call Records
    - 1973, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Topical and Administrative files
  Topical and Administrative Files (2.5 linear ft.; 1970-2001) contains memoranda, annual reports, statistics, notes, poetry, correspondence and contracts. The series documents Ozone's contacts with other social service organizations, as well as issues which have been of special concern to staff, such as collectivism, affirmative action, and "youth lib". The series also contains bylaws, fact sheets, and foster care statistics which provide background information about the organization. Some of these records supplement files in other series. The researcher is encouraged to examine the entire finding aid.
  - 1970-1992
    - Affirmative Action Collective, 1985-1989 (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Community Development Quarterly Reports, 1986-1993 (Box 6)
    - Annual Reports, 1977-1982 (Box 6)
    - Annual and Quarterly Reports, 1980-1989 (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors History, 1973-1979 (Box 6)
    - Bylaws, 1978-1990 (Box 6)
    - Catholic Social Services of Washtenaw Coati, 1970-1987 (Box 6)
    - Child Welfare licensing, 1988-1992 (Box 6)
    - Clinicing Collective Notes, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Collective Confer, circa 1980s (Box 6)
    - Collective Organization and Planning Notes, 1982-1992 (Box 6)
    - Collectivism, 1973-, circa 1980s (Box 6)
    - Community Center Coordinating Council (C4), 1973-1987 (Box 6)
    - Concerned Group for Collaborative Effort, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Congressional Testimony, 1976-1980 (Box 6)
    - Contracts with Michigan Department of Social Services, 1980-1987; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and Thank You Letters, 1976; 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "The Crisis Center as a Collective", 1982 (Box 6)
    - Fact Sheets, 1980-1982 (Box 6)
    - Financial Statements, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    - Foster Care Statistics, 1977-1980 (Box 9)
      [Restricted Access]
    - Housing facilities, 1973-1976 (Box 7)
    - Independent Living Program (ILP) Collective Notes, 1984-1986 (Box 7)
    - Independent Living Program Rap, undated (Box 7)
    - Interagency Shelter and Housing Council, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
    - Lesbian and Gay Support Group, circa 1990s (Box 7)
    - "Levels of Success and Satisfaction with Services Provided by Ozone House", 1980 (Box 7)
    - Liability information, 1982-1990 (Box 7)
    - Long Range Planning, 1979-1992 (Box 7)
    - Member Status Assessment, undated (Box 7)
    - Parks, Bob (Michigan Department of Social Services), 1990-1992 (Box 7)
    - Poetry, circa 1978-1990; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Police relations, 1987-1992 (Box 7)
    - Presidential Volunteer Action Award, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Program Performance Reporting Requirements, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
    - Restructuring, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
    - Service Delivery Outline, undated (Box 7)
    - Service Philosophy, 1985 (Box 7)
    - Sexuality Rap, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Staff
      - Cartoons, 1981 (Box 7)
      - Letters, 1981 (Box 7)
      - Newsletter, 1976-1978 (Box 7)
    - Statistics, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Washtenaw County Interagency Shelter and Housing Council, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Youth Lib Conference, undated (Box 7)
  - 1992-2001
    - Ann Arbor Community Development Dept., 1994-2001; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Application for Emergency Shelter Grant (Michigan State Housing Development Authority), 1992 (Box 7)
    - Auditor's Report, 1994; 1996 (Box 7)
    - Audited Financial Statement and other Financial Information, 1996-1999 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors: binder containing board minutes, executive director's reports, bylaws, financial material, 1995-1999 (Box 7)
    - Budget information, 1995-1997 (Box 8)
    - Grants
      - Emergency Services Grant, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Michigan Dept. of Social Services, 1992-1993 (Box 8)
      - United Way Application, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Guidelines for Non-Profit Organizations under contract with the city of Ann Arbor, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
    - Michigan State Housing Development Authority, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
    - Miller House Transitional Living Program, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Resource Training Packet, 1998 (Box 8)
    - Street Outreach Proposal, 1998 (Box 8)
    - Zoning Board of Appeals (Ann Arbor), 1998; 1 folders (Box 8)
      (opposition of Oxbridge Neighborhood to installation of Ozone House in residential neighborhood)
- Visual Materials, 1970-1994
  Visual Materials (videotapes, VHS and open reel, and 1 oversize folder; c.1970-1994) includes videotapes and posters. The videotapes include a 1985 public service announcement for runaways.
  - Posters, circa 1970s (Folder 1)
  - Videotapes
    - Runaway Public Service Announcement, 1985; VHS videotape (Box 8)
    - Interview with volunteers and foster parents, 1989; VHS videotape
      - Lynn Hadley (volunteer) (Box 8)
      - Jaegers (foster parents) (Box 8)
      - Ozone House volunteers (Box 8)
      - Volunteers and foster parents (Box 8)
    - Videotapes from the (for training purposes, etc.), 1970s; 4 open reel videocassettes
      - Community switchboard and role play about runaway (Box 8)
      - Interview with Robin Gibber, Mike Bodine, Marion Troid, and Mike McCormick, December 1974 (Box 8)
      - Concert and Youth Liberation (Box 8)
      - Foster Care #2 (Box 8)
- Worker to Worker Notebooks, 1972-1982
  [Closed for fifty years from date of creation]
  Worker to Worker Notebooks (2.5 linear ft., 1972-1982) summarize the discussions of Ozone House staff members with troubled young persons and concerned relatives. Therefore the notebooks document the range of problems which Ann Arbor teens brought to Ozone House, and the advice and solutions offered by staff members. Also, the series documents the interactions of Ozone House staff members with one another concerning policies and procedures. Interspersed with staff comments are reports and statistics from Ozone House. Also included are brochures, newsletters and fliers from other social welfare and counseling organizations in the Ann Arbor area. This series is restricted because it includes personal identifiable information.
  - December 1972-December 1974 (Box 9)
    [Closed until Jan. 1, 2025 ]
  - December 1974-October 1977 (Box 10)
    [Closed until Jan. 1, 2028 ]
  - November 1977-1982 (Box 11)
    [Closed until Jan. 1, 2032 ]